hi welcome back to the alarm room and
this is geshe michael roach
and we're ready now to start uh the
actual
uh back into the alarming text and
what's exciting
is that we have reached
okay and it means
this is an announcement in the text that
we have reached
the 17th day of teaching so
don't forget that this entire book
was a 24-day teaching by the great
pabonko rinpoche
who was also a teacher of my teachers
teacher
and one of the greatest books ever
written in tibet
maybe the greatest okay and ninja dumber
means
we're starting on the record of the 17th
day of teachings okay
and that makes us about 80 percent
finished uh you know we started this
book
i guess over 10 years ago and and
personally i'm just enjoying the book
i'm not
trying to get through it and try to
finish in this by a certain date i'm not
thinking like that
i'm trying to personally i'm trying to
enjoy it
and go through it very with a lot of
pleasure and enjoyment i don't know
maybe like people drink a fine wine i
don't know
but just you know you don't rush to
finish the bottle
you just sit and enjoy it right so
we're enjoying the alarm room together
and personally i don't care how long it
takes i think we should do it
very deeply and we in this course
we are going to do it deeply okay so
we're about 80
finished there's 24 days total
but don't forget uh we finished two of
those days already
towards the end and that's the teaching
on meditation and wisdom emptiness
and we did those at the beginning of
this 10 years
because we wanted to use the meditations
during the long-run classes
so we've actually finished about 80
percent of the text
and i guess we can finish in about four
or five more years
and then i made you a promise for
dessert we're going to go to the great
greatest emptiness teaching of ever
the emptiness teaching in this islam
realm called the gift of liberation
thrust into the palm of your hand
the presentation of emptiness is
actually not that
long and the reason is that
uh tonka did it so well and so long with
manjushri's help
i think pablo and pate was thinking ah
we don't have to
we don't have to cover it that much here
so we're going to go after we finish
this lauren
we're going to go study the emptiness
chapter in the meditation chapter
from uh som copper's great book on the
steps of the past which is lomium chimo
and that will take us about six years so
don't worry
uh we have only about ten years left to
go okay and then you know don't
don't gobble down this uh fine wine you
know enjoy it
and have fun uh i
it's a way of life lamrim is not a book
uh lamrim is a way of life for the rest
of your life and if you can get lomrim
teachings
for most of your adult life which i did
you'll be very grateful it's it keeps
you
it keeps your life going straight uh
through all the changes that we have in
our life you know the lam rim can be the
one steady thing
that you keep doing through your whole
life okay here we go
all right ninja dumber
means uh let's talk i'd like to give you
a quotation
from that great bodhisattva girl chimbu
shivaha shantideva okay and here's the
quotation
[Music]
i bow down to that precious state of
mind to the jewel
of that state of mind well what state of
mind are you talking about shanty david
he says
well there's a state of mind that
if you have it and someone
bows down to you they make incredible
good karma we talked about it in the
coffee shop
if you're a secret bodhisattva which you
can be
and you're sitting in the coffee shop
and somebody offers you a coffee
they get like a billion years of good
karma okay it's so cool
it's so sexy to be the person
who can quietly make other people a
billion years of good karma
just by buying a coffee from them okay
but obviously if they make a
prostration to you they will get intense
good karma
now comes contradict controversial part
khanna
wouldn't it be cool to be the kind of
person
that if someone hurt you they would make
good karma what
if someone hurt you they would make good
karma
come on guess what we know many examples
if you do bad thing to bodhisattva you
get bad karma for a long long time
yeah but something happens cool even if
you heard of bodhisattva you get
dendelle
dendelle means you make a common
connection with them you see
even if you yell at a bodhisattva or you
say something bad about
bodhisattva then of course you make a
bad seed
but you also make a connection seed
with the bodhisattva it's very
interesting and that will bring you
happiness for
millions of lifetimes okay it's so cool
so if i can become bodhisattva
if i can have bodhisattva's vision
then of course if someone serves me a
coffee secretly i will give them a
billion years of good karma
that's sweet oh and even if they yell at
me or they call me stupid i guess
michael you're stupid
then uh of course they will make some
bad karma but
they will make this karma of connection
with the bodhisattva
and that karma's much more powerful and
they will have this very sweet karma
of connection with the bodhisattva so uh
shandy davis bowing down to bodhichitta
because
of its beautiful qualities it's like a
jewel it's like a wish-giving joke
you know even if you do the worst thing
possible to bodhisattva
and you criticize them and spit on them
or something you
you you say bad things about them uh
certain kind
even up to thank you
uh up to those that bodhichitta
can still give you buddhahood okay even
even from making a bad connection with
the bodhisattva
because you made a connection with the
bunny supper
that bodhichitta is so powerful that
somehow it's going to take
those other people to enlightenment when
they criticize you
so that's kind of cool right chanduki
senki penang
this sunni means our llama started out
the 17th day
by reminding us of how cool is
bodhichitta soon means he
he he reminded us penan goshi means
he threw in a couple of more benefits
about bodhichitta that he did not
mention
in the previous day he added some more
and
what's the new benefit we have insulted
bodhisattva
and you make a connection to become a
buddha yay
okay
there's a very important word here
called simba
okay z-a-n-p-a okay simba
very very important word and it
it's very difficult to translate into
english but it means
i don't know when you're in high school
and your hormones are flowing strong
which in some men don't finish until
you're 85 or
90 i don't know uh but you fall in love
with every girl you see
on the street you know and uh like we
were talking about don juan right
no don quixote sorry
let he fall in love with this uh this
bar girl you know what's her name
i forgot
i forgot her name anyway uh
if the young man fall in love with this
girl in high school then all the time
he's thinking about her all the time
he he he's driving he's thinking about
everything reminds him
of this new girl he met in the high
school and that's called
simba in tibetan that's called simba his
mind is captured
by this feelings for the girl in the
bodhisattva's mind
simba captured by this feeling
that i would like to become a buddha for
everybody okay simba that's simba okay
means once you
once you have bodhichitta stuck in your
mind
like that cute girl's picture in your
okay from that time they all sang you
take change
of georgie then anything you do
becomes uh a cause for your
enlightenment okay
once you are thinking about this girl
meaning this buddhahood then it doesn't
matter what you do
that becomes a cause for buddhahood and
we have a picture here uh
is a guy taking a walk with his
dog and his or a lady taking a walk with
her husband and her dog
just if a body suffer
is got the bodhisattva state of mind
in their mind but it's not a vision of
dancing between planets if they have
that in their mind
then everything they do is dumb
that's really cool okay like you don't
have to go
to the temple and read a medicine buddha
sutra
go for a walk with your dog and your
husband
and you that's dharma if you're thinking
about
this vision that i would like to dance
between many planets
and help people if you're thinking about
that then everything you do you brush
your teeth you know
i don't know you watch netflix
everything you do becomes therma okay
it's very
beautiful it's very very cool all right
okay
let's go to the next sentence
now he says let's put it in the context
of practice
okay means okay
how does this bodhisattva's vision gonna
affect your buddhist practice
[Music]
okay forget how gong forget meditating
on
medicine buddha dead son forget during
medicine bitter mantras okay
check your map even if you don't do
anything jupa don't think about those
high high practices
drupa nyams and langje by the way this
ma tim is not a negative
it's it's the second half of she okay
it's interesting so you have to be
careful it means the
the super foundation okay like the
mother foundation shima
chandra narnikyan
he says forget you know
secret mantras forget meditation on
medicine
even medicine bruner right now if you
focus on
this feeling that i would like to dance
between the planet
and help all the beings there you focus
on that feeling
and that's enough for your practice
that's extremely
powerful vajrayana practice
is to love other people enough that you
want to dance between a billion planets
and help them okay keep that vision in
your mind
and it's it's it's as powerful as tantra
okay keep that vision in your mind okay
then he says in the next sentence
means a mountain uh like when we do the
mandala we say really
which means mountain right mount meru
and uh
tong means you know empty so ritong
means
you climb up to the himalayan mountains
you find a cave and you start meditating
shin jindashi gongko doesn't matter
what you do by the way tim the cool is
new for you
k-h-u-l and that means
act like you're doing something okay
like you go through the motions
it's cool it doesn't mean cool
okay so when you add it to a verb
it means yeah yeah you you look like
you're a meditator you look like oh you
went up on a mountain
and you're sitting in a cave and you
look like you're meditating you're going
through all the motions check them but
go if you don't have this bodhisattva's
vision you can spend a whole lifetime
in a meditation cave in the himalayas
and you will not get closer
niuru you will not get closer
to buddhahood at all chung say
okay you will not get closer to
buddhahood if you don't have this
vision okay none good
so this is an important new word for
everybody
say
the palm of your hand and it also means
the sole of your foot okay
this is where you get your wheels when
you get the marks of a buddha for
example
on your till okay but in tibetan
spoken tibetan when you say uh
put it in your palm in your hand similar
to the title
of this book it means keep that as your
main practice
okay there's something you got a picture
for me
yeah keep this feeling
not next yeah in the palm of your hand
okay it means
till took down the till two dumb guitar
means
keep that as your number one practice
okay two thumb
it means in the palm of your hand in
tibetan means
keep that vision of you dancing between
planets
keep that as your main main main
practice okay that's called
that practice that's in the middle of
the palm of your hand it's something you
carry around all the time
okay all right uh
let's go back to tibetan
[Music]
this is the most beautiful part of this
tibetan and i'm gonna say that about a
hundred times
uh
if you just know the instructions okay
you need the instruction manual
for how to get bodytalk that's all he
says that's all
look there's one page list
stuff you have to do then you get buddy
tina okay
just look there's a very easy list you
just
follow seven instructions
and you get there okay so let's do it
together okay
just seven instructions you don't have
to meditate for 20 years
there's just seven steps seven easy
steps
just do them and then you get it okay
good
they're good so may not not too good so
means our llama
impressed enough just do those
i'm gonna teach you some instructions
and you just follow them okay
every time that you started dharma
teaching you have to get your students
into the mood you know you have to say
look you know the virus was
nothing you know uh four million people
three million people die
is nothing seven billion people died
that's something
eight billion people died that's
something okay so don't forget
why are we doing lumbrium the virus was
nothing three million people isn't
nothing seven billion people gonna die
if we don't do something they're not
gonna die from the virus
they're gonna die from getting old and
die okay
we already had a virus before the virus
it was called living
you know and we're all gonna die from it
you know
so uh he says don't forget the
motivation why we are here
why we are studying learning don't
forget okay that
on the seventeenth day the teacher
papankarimpuche reminded us
why we were here okay so never forget
when the
song was such a nam soon jay that
jamie's afterwards okay and it means
he went through the outline
that we covered in the last course which
i just did with you the ten benefits of
buddhichita okay
chanting
he reviewed the ten benefits of
this vision of a bodhisattva which we
just did in the last class
tanyang gombola kya shinsei and he
talked about
you're going to build this seven steps
to bodhichitta
you're going to build them on upeksha
what's a picture of timothy
economy yeah so don't forget you
you gotta have equanimity before you can
build love on top of it okay
you have to treat people equally before
you can learn to love people
okay before you can really learn to love
people
you have to see people as equal okay so
he
he explained it zayn means he ex
he repeated from the last class and then
we went on to the new class so here's
the new class
you guys should learn the word marsha
okay marsha
in the second line first part of the
second line here
yeah and this is what we're going to
focus on today
and it's called marsha okay marshay
means
realize they are your mother okay my
shame means
realize they are your mother this is the
first step
to developing that bodhisattva's vision
okay you have to understand they are
your mother okay
then he says did you like a shintoka
digital
it's extremely difficult to reach
okay this gear means mind
to develop this in your mind is
extremely difficult okay
to to really believe
that the people around you have been
your mother
is extremely difficult
but if you don't get passed through this
first step of the
seven you can forget trying to be a
bodhisattva if you don't
get to the point where you realize
that all the people around you have been
your mom before
forget being a buddy something not
possible okay so okay
but bonkers look i know it's difficult
it's not easy
but we gotta start there you gotta
recognize that everyone has been your
mother okay
dila nintendo means so you gotta work
hard on this okay
you gotta focus at the beginning
on treating seeing
people have been your mom that's all you
have to focus on that
at the beginning okay and then he says
means relation like relative
in your family tartu means ultimate
relative
which is your mom okay
uh if you can't
recognize that everybody around you has
been your mom
then you don't have the kawa what's that
mean you guys do you remember
jigme keller you don't have kelvins
yeah shay means like doji chipper what's
that mean
you cut you cut the possibility
of buddhahood if if you can't reach
this state of mind where you see that
everyone has been your mom
means you don't have the good karma to
be a
buddha you will never be a guru kawatik
that
karmic seed is cut in you
okay you don't have a choice you have to
you have to work on this
idea that everyone has been your mom
the most important one i love this
picture of my mom
this is me uh with my mom
and uh i don't know i i
and i i tell you i'm 68 years old my mom
died
[Music]
over 40 years ago uh
i don't think about her as much as i
used to i
i mean i used to think about her all the
time used to cry all the time
uh and then slowly as you get older and
older older and you start
you don't think about your mom as much
but if you do think about your mom
the point of this meditation is let's go
back
to remembering what our mom did for us
and let's go back to remembering
that everyone has been my mother okay
he says
[Music]
look you can meditate on emptiness it's
okay
you can learn all the arguments for for
emptiness
uh yeah you can spend your time rigbeck
gold num dung
mumbo means you can use logic
and reasonable thinking to establish
some domini
yeah you could you could spend your time
like that say
something
[Music]
getting to see that everyone has been
your mom
is not as hard as that okay i admit
it's harder to see emptiness okay
[Music]
uh that's that's i
i i understand that seeing emptiness is
difficult
and yeah if you if you tell me is
bodhichitta easier or is emptiness
easier i gotta say maybe emptiness is
really hard but
dilla lung she keeps some
but i have to say something about
recognizing
that everyone around you is your mom
it's not gonna be enough to just think
about it
okay you can't sit there oh guess what i
said everyone's been my mom
okay so you're not gonna get the
bodhichitta that way it's not enough
he says
those of you who are have a high
spiritual iq
you're gonna have to use you're gonna
have to think your way
through this kind of love you're gonna
through this kind of love and then you
can reach it but you gotta learn to
think
clearly okay you clear thinking
is how you're gonna reach this kind of
love not by saying oh my mom was so
beautiful and i love my mom
and i feel good about my mom and i wish
that my mom was still alive
that's okay but if you don't think your
way
through it he says you will never reach
bodhichitta you have to think your way
to that kind of love okay gushing then
he quotes
namdo okay namdael is a book by master
damakurti
it's called promontortica it's a
commentary on accurate perception
and it is the mother buddhist book about
clear thinking how to be how to think
clearly the next picture here
you can see uh smoke
uh coming up out of a forest and
this picture is extremely important for
a buddhist
okay this picture if a buddhist sees
this picture they say ah
i know what you're talking about i know
what you're talking about
under that smoke there's definitely a
fire in this forest
there's a big red fire behind the green
trees
but we can't see it right all we can see
is the smoke
if there's smoke there's fire if there's
smoke
there's fire in this case in the alarm
rim
the fire means everyone you ever met in
your life
was your mom that's the fire what's the
smoke
we have to look for the smoke we have to
look for
the proof that the people around me have
been my mom
okay we have to try to find the proof
the smoke is the proof that there's a
fire
now what's the proof that everyone has
been my mom you know guess what
give me the proof it's not enough for
the llama to describe it to you
and it's not enough to meditate about
how much you love your mom
you must understand the reason why
everyone
has definitely been your mom okay
there's no choice
you you gotta use a special kind of
thinking to prove to yourself
beyond the dog that everyone has been
your mom
and until you go through that mental
exercise it's hopeless
you you won't be able to get body chin
it's never gonna happen okay
so now we're gonna go on a big trip in
the next class
the next class is a long class okay so
but get some popcorn before you start
the next class
and i'm not going to stop it might take
a while okay
but we're going to go he mentions
dharma kirti and he mentions that
dharmakurti proved that everyone has
been your mom
but he doesn't give you the whole proof
so guess where we're going to go
we're going to go to dhamma kirti and
we're going to go through dharma kirti's
proof it's tough
and it's delicious okay so i'll see in
the next class
we'll prove that everyone's been your
mom okay
see you then